CLAUS WILKE: Yeah, hello.
It's great to be here.
My name is Claus Wilke.
I'm with the University
of Texas at Austin.
And today I'm talking
about work that
has been sponsored
by the R Consortium,
that slide there prominently
featured in the bottom.
And it's about improving
text rendering in ggplot.
So a common problem
that probably
all of you at some
point have run into
is you may want to mix italics
and normal text in ggplot.
So in my day work,
I'm a biologist,
so it's a very common
problem for biologists.
You have species names that
are supposed to be in italics,
but then you have other
text surrounding it
that shouldn't be in italics.
So how can we make that happen?
And so just to give you an
example of how that may arise,
here's a Stack Overflow issue
that's asking that question.
For my plot figure, I want to
label the categories on a bar
plot with the first
word being italicized
while the following
words are not italicized.
I want the category
labels to look as follows.
And so there's a
typical biology example.
There's a bacterial name.
I'm not trying to pronounce it.
And then OTU 1 operational
taxonomic unit--
that's a biology term.
But in any case, this
should be italics.
This should not be italics.
All right?
So let's look a little
more into the example code
and data that comes
with this issue.
So there's a made-up data
set that the person provided.
We have, in the first
column, the name
of the bacterial species.
Then we have these OTUs.
Then we have a name
column that combines
the bacterial
species and the OTUs,
and then we have
some numeric value.
And so the person
was turning this
into a bar plot with just
three lines of ggplot.
You take the data, pipe it into
ggplot, put name on x and value
on y, but then we
flip the coordinates
so we get a horizontal plot.
And of course, you see
the problem in this plot
is that the bacteria
names are not in italics.
So how can we
solve that problem?
Now, the common solution
that you will find for that
is some sort of plot math.
So this is the accepted
solution on Stack Overflow.
You can make a
vector of expressions
and apply it to the labels
argument and scale x discrete.
And so the code that
makes the magic happen
is this code here--
quote italic, parentheses,
single quote, double quote,
comma, x bracket 1.
I cannot write that code.
I'm sure there's people in this
room who can write that code,
and I salute you.
I cannot, and I don't want to.
I would rather write my own
text rendering software in C++.
And so that's what I've done.
OK.
But that leads us to the
question, so how should
we specify formatted text?
So let's make first a
slightly simple example.
Instead of the axis tick labels,
let's just look at the title.
OK.
I want a title "species
names are in italics,"
and italics should
be in italics.
And maybe I've
already given it away.
So I put italics in stars.
Anybody that has used
Markdown knows this, right?
If you're using R Markdown, if
you want something in italics,
you put stars around it.
And so that's what this
package, ggtext, facilitates.
So as of right now, it's
still in development.
You have to install
it from GitHub.
But it's essentially
ready to go.
It's just waiting for the
next release of ggplot.
So sometime within the
next two to three months,
this should be on CRAN.
So I've now loaded the package.
Nothing has happened
yet because I haven't
changed anything in the code.
It wouldn't be good if
just randomly, stars were
interpreted as markdown,
because maybe sometimes you
actually want to have
stars in your text.
So we have to tell
ggplot that now it should
interpret this as markdown.
And so I've hooked this up with
a theme system so that now--
if you've ever used
themes in ggplot,
usually plot.title tells us
how the title of the plot
is styled.
And normally, you would
write element_text(),
and then you can use that to
change the color, and so on.
And now I've written
this element_markdown(),
and so now you see this has
been interpreted as markdown.
And so now "in
italics" is in italics.
OK.
So now let's apply this
to the original problem.
So the additional
issue here now is
that we have these
different species names,
and we don't want to
manually put them into stars.
We want to automate that.
Right?
And so there, a really,
really good companion package
is the glue package.
If you're not
routinely using glue,
I encourage you to look into it.
Glue allows you to very quickly
paste pieces from your data
frame into strings of text.
So I'm taking the data
here, pipe into mutate,
and then I create a new name
column where I call glue.
And then here I have this
star, and then bactname
is the column name that has the
bacterial name in curly braces.
And that tells glue don't
write bactname into the string,
but actually pull it
from the data frame,
and then here the
same with OTUname.
And so that now
creates this table,
where now you see
I have nice stars
around the bacterial names.
And so now I pipe
this into ggplot
with the element markdown.
So now it's, of
course, the axis.text.y
that I want to change.
And now you see
this is in italics.
This is not.
[APPLAUSE]
OK.
I see this solves a problem.
So now you might say, OK.
Your plots are boring.
Don't you ever use color?
I do.
So let's do
something with color.
Actually, let's
add a color column.
I'm doing a little bit of
a trick, so if Hadley--
Hadley is not in
the room, right?
He would say, you're
circumventing the scale
system.
Yes.
In this case, that's
the right way to do it.
So I'm adding--
I'm adding a color
vector, so these are just
colors that I chose..
And now what I'm--
I'm still using
glue, but now you
may see here I'm actually
writing a little bit of HTML.
So this is the italics tag now,
and I'm using inline styling
to get the color in there.
And with that, I can
actually have now colors.
So the trick that
I'm using here is
I'm using scale_fill_identity().
So I'm mapping color
onto fill, and then
scale_fill_identity(), instead of trying
to set up a color mapping,
it just takes the actual
colors that are in the column.
Now, one other thing
that you may notice--
it's a topic that is
very dear to my heart.
You may notice that
visually, these colors
and these colors look
kind of the same,
Right they match very well.
But I'm actually setting the
transparency to 0.5 here.
So the bars are actually
at 50% transparency,
and then they look
the same as the text,
which is completely opaque.
And that's just how our
visual system works.
When you color large areas, you
need the color to be lighter.
It's a very common
problem that I
see when people color text that
the text becomes too light.
The text always needs
to use a darker color
to look the same as a large
area that you color the same.
So this worked out well.
So if you make the
color 50% transparent,
it's going to be about right.
OK.
So now we're getting
ambitious, right?
What else can I do?
So this is another issue
from Stack Overflow.
It's another biological problem.
So it's made-up data.
The key thing here is
there are these phases.
So these are phases
of cell division--
again, a biological example.
And so this person had
these different images.
And so this image
corresponds to this phase.
This image corresponds
to this phase, and so on.
And so the question
was, can we somehow
get the images into the figure?
And we can.
So now we're using the image
tag where we're loading
or we're setting the images.
So in this particular case, it's
in a folder on my hard drive,
but you can pull them from
a web page if you want.
That works just fine.
We put a break tag
and then the word,
and we stick it into ggplot.
The only other thing
is lineheight.
The default lineheight, for
some reason, is just too low.
It's 0.9.
I don't know why.
1.2 is a better line
height if you actually want
to have things in two lines.
And there we go.
We have the images in the
axis and the label underneath.
[APPLAUSE]
I see this solves
another problem.
Very good.
There's a few other
things that it can do.
So there's actually the
option to have text boxes
with some amount
of text wrapping.
And you can color
the background.
If you go to the website, which
is in the bottom right corner,
you can see the code that
makes this particular figure.
OK.
So everything I've shown so
far is theme elements, right?
Does this only work
for theme elements?
No.
I also have written
a geom that you
can use to use the same
text rendering in a plot.
So let's do another
common situation.
So this is the iris dataset,
which I assume everybody knows.
So we have three
species of iris flowers.
We're plotting the sepal
width against the sepal length
for the three species, and we
are putting regression lines
in here.
And so oftentimes, when
you have a plot like that,
you may want to annotate
this with, say, the r squared
of the regression line.
Right?
And so it's again the problem--
OK, how do I get the r squared
into some plot math expression
that then I can add to the plot?
And so we'll, instead
of doing that,
use the same technique here.
So let's just go through
the code quickly.
So first we calculate
the correlation.
So we take the iris
dataset, group by species,
summarize, calculate
the r squared.
So then we end up with a
table that has the species
names and the r squared, right?
And now we turn this
into our labels.
So this sepal length and
sepal width, 8 and 4.5,
those are just the
coordinates where the label
will appear in the plot.
And then again, I use
the glue function.
So I have R in
star, so it's going
to be italics,
superscript 2 because it's
going to be r squared.
And here I'm pasting in the
correlation coefficient,
and I round
it to two digits.
So in the glue package
inside the square brackets,
you can just write
regular R code,
and it gets executed
and replaced
by the resulting string.
And then this goes into ggplot
into a geom_richtext() which
takes the label and
interprets it as HTML,
and so now you have
here this label,
r squared equals whatever.
So by default, it puts a white
background and a box around it,
but all of that you can change.
You can take the box
away if you want.
You can put a different
background, and so on.
So that's really all I can do.
However, there's actually two
packages that I've written.
So this package was
the ggtext package
which provides the
interface to ggplot,
but it's really just the wrapper
around an underlying package,
so the package that
makes it all possible.
And that already is on CRAN,
and that's the gridtext package.
And so that is a great
package if you're actually
writing grid graphics codes-- so
for example, if you're writing
your own ggplot extensions.
And I've made it
so that if you're
used to writing
grid code, it should
be very easy to use
the gridtext package.
So if you've never seen grid
code, this may look scary.
But if you have seen grid code,
this should be very familiar.
So this is, so far,
just regular grid.
I have some text here,
then I set up grid graphics
parameters, so gpar
graphics parameters.
And I'm using a silly font with
some font size and a color.
And then I created
textGrob, grob stands
for graphics object,
text, the coordinates, x
and y, horizontal justification
in the graphics parameters,
and then I call the grid.draw()
function to draw it,
and I get this outcome.
OK.
And so now, in addition,
I draw the same string,
but using the richtext drawing
function from gridtext.
And so it looks like this.
So now I have richtext_grob()
text, coordinates, hjust, gp.
So it looks exactly the same.
I put a different
coordinate here
so they are in
different y locations.
This is why this is
at 0.7, this is 0.4.
But you can actually plot
them on top of each other,
and they should pretty
much look exactly the same,
and then you just draw its.
OK.
And that's it, actually.
I want to end with
one word of caution.
So you may now think, oh,
great, I can do anything.
That is not true.
You can pretty much do exactly
what I showed you and not more.
So the issue is that I'm
not handing off the HTML
to a web browser that renders
it or some professional text
rendering library.
For technical reasons,
there's just no good way right
now to achieve that.
So I had to write my own
rendering engine from scratch.
And so my approach was, OK,
what are the five things that I
can implement in a
reasonable amount of time
that really, really
make a difference?
And the number one
is italics and bold.
The number two is colors.
Number three is being
able to change fonts,
so you can change a different
font if you want to.
Number four is superscript
and subscripts,
and then number five is images.
So that's where I currently am.
You can do a lot with that.
But just this morning,
I got this bug report
that I was waiting for which
listed 100 markdown features
that don't currently work.
Yes, I know.
They don't currently work.
The truth is, my vision is to
increase the number of features
that we support.
At this point, we have
a good user interface
that I think will remain stable.
And so I can now
keep adding features.
And just eventually,
at some point,
certain things may work
that right now don't work.
But anything that works now
should continue to work.
And the R code-- sorry--
the R code should not
change going forward.
So with that, make plots
with formatted text.
[APPLAUSE]
Do you want to
take some questions?
Yeah, yeah.
All right, great.
We have a couple
minutes for questions
here, so let me
go down the list.
All right.
There were a lot of
questions in here
that you just covered at
the end, like what else,
what else is available.
So I will scroll through those.
Do you have any
thoughts on adding
shorthand markdown-ish syntactic
sugar around the HTML tags
for this work?
I'm not sure I
understand the question.
So the way that this
whole thing works
is it actually-- it
takes the markdown.
It sends it through the
regular markdown package that
is part of R, which
turns it into HTML,
and then the HTML gets rendered.
So anything that
you're used to doing
in Markdown works in theory
as long as the resulting HTML
is actually supported.
Right?
So going forward,
what I need to do
is I need to support
more HTML features.
And actually, the
biggest issue right
now is I need to
support more CSS,
because that's the next
big stumbling block
for a lot of obvious features
that you would want to have.
And then the
markdown should just
come by itself through the
existing markdown package.
Awesome, thanks.
All right.
I was really happy to
see some glue in there,
because I love that package.
But we have some folks
in the audience who
wanted to know, what is
the advantage of using glue
over paste() or paste0()?
So the advantage
of glue() over paste()
is just that it may be slightly
easier to write, in particular
if you have a lot of things.
Right?
So where was it?
Somewhere here.
Actually, let's
go to the colors.
Sorry.
I don't know the
way around my own--
ah.
I mean, paste() would
work just the same.
If you like paste(), use paste().
But I find this
very easy to read.
These curly braces are
very low overhead, right?
So it's very easy to just
look at the piece of text that
comes out and says,
yes, this looks correct,
versus with paste(), it gets a bit
more complicated to figure out
what the final output
actually will be.
Here's one about--
do you have any tips
for incorporating
non-standard fonts into
plots that might not
be available on your machine?
OK.
So this-- first of all, this
package doesn't solve that.
This package will work with
any font that works regularly
in your R setup.
Right? so the problem
of having other fonts--
like Thomas is working on that.
The long-term goal
is that any font
that you have installed on
your machine should just work.
And actually, on Macs, that
actually works reasonably well,
honestly.
Any font that the operating
system knows, I can use.
Like I installed, actually,
Font Awesome from the web,
and then I could put
little icons into plots.
I didn't demonstrate that today,
but that worked just fine.
So as long as R
supports the font,
it will work in this case.
But how to make that happen,
that's really for Thomas.
Excellent.
All right.
And lastly, of course, where
are your slides available?
Where can you be found for
the rest of the conference?
I completely
forgot about that.
So I actually tweeted
it out right before--
actually, earlier this morning.
So if you go @clauswilke,
that's my Twitter handle.
And the last tweet I made--
the second-to-last tweet
I made is the slides.
All right.
Thank you so much, Claus.
[APPLAUSE]